[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
all right
let's we want to we want to move on to a
slippery and somewhat uh abstract and
frankly a little bit difficult subject
the notion well first of all the subject
is tensor Cal calculus we've done about
everything that you can do with tensor
algebra and tensor arithmetic adding
subtracting we we haven't talked about
adding and subtracting tensors but you
can add and subtract tensors just make
sure the things that you're adding have
matching indices don't try to add
something like
VN to W subm that will not be a good
operation if you want to add V and W
add contravariant components or
covariant components don't try to add a
tensor with two indices to a tensor with
three indices that won make sense what
will you have at the end a scramble of
garbage
um but as long as you're adding things
which are compatible but they have their
indices in the same place same type of
indices then tensors add that simply
means that the sums and differences of
tensors are again tensor
meaning to say that they transform the
same way as The
Originals
uh now why do we introdu first of all
why do we introduce tensors let's
let's let's uh go back a
step and talk about why they're
important we want
to discuss the properties of geometries
of various kinds
geometry could be a sphere it could be a
Taurus it could be just a it doesn't
have to be two-dimensional either but
for two-dimensional could be a plane it
could be a hilly uh surface which is
highly
irregular um and of course we don't
really need to draw coordinates on it
there are no coordinates really drawn on
the earth of course we can talk about
properties of the earth without actually
introducing coordinates most likely we
could Express all of physics without
coordinates without uh introducing
coordinates but it would be difficult
when we actually come to compute things
it's very convenient to be able to
discuss the components of um of vectors
tensors and so
forth after all I mean computation is
about numbers not abstract symbols and
when you come to actually compute to
throw it onto a computer or something
you want to put in numerical values for
things and the components of vectors and
tensors and so forth are the way that
you describe them in
practice now tensors have the very
important property oh wow all right
let's start the the the relationships
that we're actually interested in are
relationships which in a sense are
independent of the coordinates which
don't depend on your choice of
coordinates uh the fact that the Earth
is a sphere doesn't depend on what
coordinates you use the fact that its
curvature is everywhere is the same well
of course it's not quite true so let's
say what is true the fact that the uh
Earth is almost a sphere which is
slightly flattened you don't need
coordinates to express that uh the fact
that Mount Everest is a lump on the
surface of the Earth again you don't
need coordinates to describe that those
things are things which are coordinate
independent
um but what we want to do is Express
those same kinds of facts geometric
facts in terms of coordinates that means
we want to write
equations which perhaps the numerical
left side and the numerical right side
do depend on the coordinates but the
fact that the left side equals the right
side should not depend on coordinates
right so it's important to isolate
quantities that have the following
property that if their
components are equal if there's a rule
or if there's a fact that the components
of one tensor for example or one object
and this object happens to have
indices we may or may not be a tensor
may or may not transform the right way
it has some
indices in other words there are
whatever number of such objects there
are you lay them out in a in a matrix if
you like if we know that in one
coordinate system let's say the x
coordinate system if we know that
two matrices or two sorry uh two
tensors are are
equal in the x coordinate system then it
must
follow or we're looking for definitions
so that the equality in one coordinate
system will imply the equality in all
other coordinate systems in that sense
if we can write our equations and our
laws of physics in terms of objects
which if they are equal in one
coordinate system then they are
necessarily equal in all coordinate
systems then effectively we've expressed
the laws in a way which don't depend on
the coordinates they don't depend on the
coordinates maybe perhaps the numerical
value of the leftand side and the right
hand side depend on the coordinates but
the fact that they're equal
doesn't all right we can write that
another way we can always take any such
equation subtract this and write that
it's equal to
zero it's an interesting fact the
equality sign is completely unnecessary
in mathematics
you could make it a rule put everything
over on one side and whenever you see an
expression assume that it's zero and
then you never need the zero sign you
never need uh you never need the
equality this is zero because that's our
definition but we don't do that we allow
ourselves to uh use equals at
zero and so the same
statement is the same statement that I
just made is that we would like to
express our equations of physics in a
form something is equal to zero and if
that something is equal to zero in one
coordinate system then it's zero in
every coordinate system we would like to
find objects which have that
property those objects are
tensors how do I know that well let's
just remind ourselves how tensors
transform a tensor for example a vector
let's just take the simplest case a
vector
VN of Y in other words the components of
a vector in the y-coordinate system are
equal to the components of
Y sorry of uh V the same Vector in the x
coordinate system we can put an R here
and then there is a let's see which way
does it go n is downstairs so there's a
Dy n
DX R oops put the n
r all right so now it's quite
easy if all of the components not just
one of the components but if all of the
components of VX are equal to zero then
all of the components of v y are equal
to zero obviously just from this
equation here if all of the components
of V are equal to zero in other words if
V is a vector which is equal to zero
then its components are zero either in
the y-coordinates or the x coordinates
so with transformation properties like
this or more complicated ones involving
several indices for example if we have
some
tensor uh let's put one index upstairs
another index
downstairs in the Y coordinates that
would be equal
to uh dym
by
dxr
DX
s by Dy n time
T
RS all right again if all of in the X in
the x
coordinates if all of the components of
T are zero in the x coordinate then all
of them are zero in the y-coordinates
that's the importance of
tensors that if there if you have an
equation which is true in one set of
coordinates and you know that the
objects are tensors you don't have to
check them in other coordinate systems
now we're going to discover that not
everything is a tensor in
particular ordinary
derivatives of tensors are not tensors
not everything that you can write down
is a tensor
but still we want to Define some sort of
notion of the way a tensor varies from
place to place it's going to be
important to have an idea of how things
vary from place to place so we have to
have some concept of the notion of a
derivative of a tensor let's go through
why why the why it's
problematic
okay let's start with scalers
incidentally the transformation property
of a scaler is
Trivial if the if the if the scaler is V
is fi we call typical Scala
fi if its value at a certain point in
space is fi in the x
coordinates then it's also fi in the Y
coordinat
if the points X and Y correspond to the
same actual material Point here on the
Blackboard just different coordinate
representations of the same point so F
transforms in a trivial way doesn't
transform at all uh obviously if you
know that f is equal to zero in one
reference frame you know that it's zero
in all reference frames simply because
it's the same in all reference frames
now let's come to the derivative of
f with respect to X the derivative of f
with respect to XM let's
say all right that is in fact a vector
it's a vector with a covariant index
here but let's just see why is it true
that if mathematically it's uh
straightforward why or
the um the fact that if d by DX is equal
to Z then d by d y is equal to Z
mathematically it's just that d by
Dy let's call it y n is equal to
DX M by d y n *
F uh times the derivative of Pi with
respect to XM
so if f is constant and has no
derivatives with respect to X clearly
its derivatives with respect to Y are
also zero but let's just think about it
uh from an intuitive point of view to
say that fi has no derivatives in
particular let's imagine has no
derivatives anywhere what does that mean
that means it's constant and it doesn't
vary from place to place it's a scalar
you could go and measure it in every
point in space and it's constant like
the temperature being the same
everywhere as in the room
here if a thing is constant it's going
to be constant no matter what the
coordinates are I don't care whether I
use polar coordinates I use elliptical
hyperbolic SM of its coordinates doesn't
matter whatever coordinates I use if the
temperature is constant in this room
it's going to be constant in every set
of
coordinates so it stands to reason that
if the derivative of f is equal to zero
everywhere in space with respect to X
then it's also going to be zero with
respect to Y so a perfectly good
description of the air in this room in
thermal equilibrium is that the
temperature with respect the derivative
of the temperature with respect to the x
coordinates is equal to zero and you
don't have to ask Will it also be zero
in the y-coordinates
for the reasons I've just explained now
let's come to vectors we're going to see
that the problem is more
complicated let's begin with a
vector which is constant on the
Blackboard in space flat space good old
cartisian
coordinates let's not get fancy with
curved space or anything just ordinary
flat
space could be two-dimensional could be
three-dimensional but let's take the
Blackboard which is two-dimensional
uh let's put some cartisian
coordinates and let's also Imagine a
vector
field which is constant in space now
what that means is it points in the same
direction everywhere and it has the same
length
everywhere just the obvious meaning of
saying a vector is constant so every
place in space that Vector is exactly
the same
now what can you say about the
components of this Vector As you move
from point to point in the same
coordinates in these same coordinates
X1 and
X2 for example let's take the uh the
covariant components covariant
components being the projections onto
the axes it's pretty obvious that the
components are also constant so to say
that a vector is constant it looks like
what it says is that the
components of the
vector what did I say a covariant vector
or a contra let's say contar a covariant
components take any
component and Vary it in any direction
if the vector is constant it looks like
it says that the components are constant
but now let's come and introduce some
curved coordinates into space same
physical fact the vector points in the
same direction everywhere but now let's
uh let me redraw it I think I'll redraw
it with some curvy linear coordinates
exactly the same
situation so the situation now is we
have some some curvy linear
coordinates and we have a constant
Vector it means physically the vector
points in the same direction
everywhere what about the covariant
components of the vector as I move from
place to place you think that
constant remember what the covariant
components are they're the projection
onto the
axes but the axes are bending and SW and
moving around on
you uh in one place the axes might look
like that someplace else they might look
like
this the same
Vector will'll have this might be your
X1 component this might be your X2
component now this might be your X1
component and this might be your X2
component pointing an entirely different
directions the same
Vector exactly the same Vector pointing
in exactly the same direction I don't
think I made that look the same
direction did
I the components will be
different the lesson is that just
because a vector is physically constant
from point to point in space it does not
mean that its components are constant in
space why
not the components of a vector depend on
two things they depend on the direction
and magnitude of the vector and also the
orientation of the axes even if the
vector doesn't change when you move from
place to place the um the axes
do so
yeah to say the vector is pointing in
the same direction and has the same
magnitude
implies a third coordinate system
that is transposable it applies to both
of them right I don't know what that
means two coordinate systems in this
particular case one of them is good old
cartisian coordinates on the
Blackboard and we imagine you know they
just good old intuitive cartisian
coordinates and the vector is constant
which means in cartisian coordinates it
means the components are constant the
same situation when we lay some curvy
linear
coordinates on the Blackboard or
incidentally we could change from one
cartisian coordinate system to another
we could rotate or translate the
cartisian components as long as the
components as long as the coordinates
are cartisian then
this the components of the vector will
be the same everywhere but now we lay on
top of it
a curved coordinate system where the
direction and spacing for example
between the coordinates varies from
place to place and now the components
will not be constant as I said it's
because the components depend both on
the vector and the orientation of the
coordinates if the coordinates are
flopping around as you move around the
components will also
be
so d v by DX equal 0 does not
imply does not imply that the v in the x
coordinate system the coordinate the
components in the x coordinate system
relative to the X
axes then being constant which is the
same as thing the derivatives are zero
does not say that the VM in the Y
coordinates this means the components
not only are they functions of Y but
they're the components in the Y along
the y axis it does not
say that these are
zero no such
implication what does that tell us
that tells us that the derivatives of V
with respect to X or with respect to Y
don't transform as a tensor if they
did then if they were zero in one frame
it would imply they was zero in the
other frame frame means a set of
coordinates here so derivatives of
tensors derivatives of scalers are
perfectly good vectors but derivatives
of vectors meaning to say the derivative
of the components they don't transform
as the components of
tensors that's a general
rule and you have to do
something you have to do something a
little trickier and a little more
complicated to Define derivatives of
tensors to make them tensors the process
is called covariant
differentiation now the covariant is not
because it has to do with a lower index
here it's another completely different
use of the term
covariant
uh what it means what it implies is it's
a form of
differentiation which you can apply to
tensors which gives you back tensors in
particular you can apply it to vectors
and get back vectors so let's see if we
can figure out what kind of thing the
covariant derivative might be let's
start with a thing which is not actually
a tensor but let's check whether it's
it's a tensor or not in other words
let's sort of assume it's a tensor and
then prove that it's not all right
exactly this object let's write
tmn in fact I'll tell you what this is
intended to be a tensor but this is
intended to be a tensor in the x
coordinate frame supposing there exists
some tensor whose x components
components in the x coordinates and
x-coordinates I now mean uh again
rectangular cartisian
coordinates let's suppose that there is
some tensor
tmn of X which is
equal to the derivative of some Vector
with respect to
X in the x coordinate system then the
question is what must it be in the
y-coordinate system and in particular
when you transform it as a tensor does
it or does it not
become the derivative this is in the x
coordinate does it or does it not become
the let's call it
um well derivative of V with of Y with
respect to
YN
question and the answer as you might
guess is the answer is no they if I try
to trans form this object pretending it
was a tensor I will not get the set of
components which look like that so let's
go through it it uh it's worth our while
to do it I could just tell you what the
answer is but let's not do it let's do
it uh with some
care
okay we have an object
which I tell you is a tensor and it
happens that in the x coordinate system
its components are the derivative of x
of V with respect to xn it happens let's
ask what must its components
be in the y-coordinate system well if it
really is a
tensor then its components must be
dxr by D
ym this is under the assumption that it
really does transform as a
tensor in the one coordinates it must
be that's the assumption that tmn is a
tensor and if you know it in the x
coordinates then you can write it down
immediately in the y-coordinates but now
we can substitute what it is in the x
coordinates here and that would just
give us the derivative of XR with
respect to ym
derivative of XS with respect to
YN and now I'm just going to plug in the
assumed value of tmn of X and that's VM
D
VM of X with respect
to oh I want TRS excuse me I want
TRS so that's
DV uh
R by
DXs and my question is is this or is
this not equal to question mark is this
or is this not equal
to the
derivative
of the M I think let's see v m of of Y
with respect to
YN this symbol equals with a question
mark doesn't mean it's equals it means
is it equal not it is equal but is it
equal right is this true this is how we
might have thought just like the just
like derivatives of scalars transform as
vectors we might have thought the
derivatives of components of vectors
transform as tensors so we're checking
out is this object over here equal to
this okay so let's see if we can uh work
it
out not it's not terribly
hard
okay let's
see what can we do with this DVR ofx by
DXs time DXs by dyn does that ring a
bell
focus on this piece right over
here that's chain rule yeah that's the
chain rule so what's in the red box
there let's put what's in the red box
over here it's first of all well not
just what's in the red box but the whole
thing it's
dxr by D what is it y and
M and now if I use a chain rule I
simplify this and I just find it's the
derivative of
VR of
X but not with respect to X but with
respect to
Y with respect to Y
in and we're asking is this the same as
this no no no no no no is that what I'm
asking yeah I guess that's what I'm
asking DVM by D YN yes okay ah yes now
notice on the right side we're checking
is this equal to
this over here I have something
involving y v y over here I have
something involving VX so let's change
everything on the right hand side so
that it's related to components with
respect to X that's easy to
do we just write that VM of Y this is
derivative with respect to y
n and now how do I write VM of Y in
terms of X components
well I just write that VM
Y is D derivative of XR with respect to
ym of v r of X all I've done here was
use the
transformation from y components to X
components to rewrite what's over
here over here just pure substitution
so now we have the question is this
equal to or is it not let's write it out
again derivative with respect to
YN I realize that this is a bit tedious
and a nuisance but I wanted to do
it uh the whole thing what is it
dxr dxr by what can somebody read it to
me D Dy subm
and then the M of X right v r
ofx v r
ofx okay well let's look at it we have
here the derivative of a product the
derivative of a product is the sum of
two terms just the you the usual rule
for the derivative of product derivative
of a * B is a * the dtive of B plus b *
the derivative of a and so first of all
this derivative can hit
V that will give me a term which looks
exactly like
this it'll give me the term dxr by D
ym times
DVR of X with respect to
YN that's exactly what I have here looks
good but it's not good because it's only
one of the terms when I take the
derivative here there's another term
say what's
that I
did I did no I didn't
where the derivative of this is equal to
this sorry what did I do um no no no no
no no no no no these are not the
same here here the derivative is outside
the product here the derivative only
acts on the
V look at the difference here we have
derivative with respect to Y of a
product here we have a product of two
derivatives not the same
thing okay who asked the
question I did yeah are you are you
happy yes okay good all right so now we
work this out the first term is gotten
by allowing the derivative with respect
to Y to hit V that does look exactly
like this so far so good but there's
something else in there and let's see
what that other thing is it's derivative
with respect to
YN of the derivative of
XR with respect to
ym that's a
thing times
VR so the answer is it is not
equal to the right hand side let's just
call it the right hand
side in other
words um this thing which I called a
tensor has not transformed as a tensor
if I insist that this is the X
components of the
tensor then it is not true that the Y
components of the tensor are just
derivatives of V with respect to
Y it's not true
okay okay
um let's see what we can
[Music]
say yeah
this
point just the just the an electric
field uh which varies from place to
place but not in Co cartisian
coordinates in some other
coordinates um and this is what happens
what happens is just because the
components of a vector may be constant
doesn't mean it's constant in all all
frames of reference this extra term gets
picked up here this is the term that's
due to the fact that the coordinates are
varying from place to place okay after
all or the directions of the coordinates
are varying from place to place if we
had um if the x coordinates were linear
functions of the y-coordinates
then these derivatives here would just
be numbers and derivatives of numbers
are zero it's because the coordinates
are
curved that this is not zero in general
and it's as I said it has to do with the
fact that the relationship between the
coordinates is varying from place to
place that's the way to think about it D
XR by d ym That's the relationship
between the x coordinates and the
y-coordinates and now that if it varies
from place to place then there's an
extra term and the extra term is
proportional to V with no
derivative all right
so uh
yeah like the picture right above yeah
exactly like the picture right above
except the red uh the red the red
vectors could also be varying from place
to place and we see that there's an
extra there's an extra
contribution look at the form of this
let me write this in some um let's
see let's see what was
the the left hand side that's I guess
this over here that's what you would get
if V if T really did transform as a
tensor all right so if T really does
transform as a tensor this has to be the
right answer it differs
from this over here it differs from what
you might have expected namely
uh this over here by this extra term
that suggests that we have to do
something a little bit different to
differentiate a tensor and to get
another
tensor okay and the
difference involves an extra term which
has not got derivatives of the vectors
in it but got but has funny derivatives
associated with the relation between
coordinates um let's see the right hand
side is by
definition tmn of
y I just read it off here assuming this
is tmn of X then this must be tmn of Y
because it transforms in the right way I
I forced it to transform in the right
way and what we see is that
um it uh well that it has this extra
term over here it's not
just where is it
it's not just what you might have
thought it was okay let's try to guess
then what the right way to differentiate
tensors
is the right way must have an extra term
that'll cancel this out let's just write
this in another form uh let me call this
object over here
let me give it a name Capital gamma how
many indices does it have it has an
index N M and R one index upstairs two
indices downstairs and it multiplies
VR
okay let's that's what we'll call
this here's more or less what we
discovered and another way of saying it
that if we want to differentiate
a
tensor its components we have to do and
get another tensor back we have to do
something a little bit trickier than
just differentiate its components namely
what we have to do is take the
derivative of V with respect to y or X
doesn't matter X the um let's call it uh
m n and then add something to it and the
thing we have to add to it is just this
G
gamma
n let's
see
uh
m
r v
r what this represents what this term
over here
represents is the fact that when you
differentiate a tensor you have to take
into account the fact that the
coordinates are varying from point to
point and so the components have some
variation that's just due to the fact
that the coordinates themselves are
flopping around so to speak there's
something here that has to go there I
haven't told you yet well I've told you
in this language over here what this
gamma is but let's
suppose now we're making a guess we're
making a guess that if we could find the
right object
gamma we could construct a new kind of
derivative a new kind of derivative of a
vector which contains an extra term not
just a derivative but an extra term
which will make this into a tensor which
will make it into a tensor which we can
call
T
MN this process of differentiating is
called coar arant derivative it's
usually written as an upside down
triangle with an in downstairs that
means covariant derivative with respect
to
xn of
VM and it's by definition equal to this
thing over here if we can figure out
what gamma
is if we can figure out what gamma is
another way to ask it is can we can we
find the thing called
gamma and I'll tell you what gamma's
going to depend on it's going to depend
on the metric tensor
it's going to depend not only on the
metric tensor but the derivatives of the
metric
tensor if the metric tensor has
derivatives that means in some way the
coordinates are flopping around if the
metric tensor is not constant it means
the coordinates are flopping around
we're going to discover that this thing
depends on the derivatives of the metric
is there an object which has the
property that when we con when we
construct the covariant Der
what occurs is actually a tensor really
is a tensor and transforms as a tensor
that'll be a brilliant achievement
because then we'll be able to write
equations such as the covariant
derivative of a vector might be equal to
some other tensor maybe a completely
different object the left hand side
could be the derivative of some electric
field the right hand side could be some
other tensor of a particular uh physical
character
and we might have a situation an
equation which says that the covariant
derivative of the um electric field is
equal to some tensor will it be true in
all reference frames yes if the left
hand side is a tensor and transforms as
a tensor and also the right hand side so
the question is can we find this
gamma and that
uh whose nature it is to make
derivatives equal to tensors well you
wrote a gamma there is yeah yeah that
that's one gamma but remember this was a
special case where the X's were
cartisian coordinates now it can happen
that we have a geometry that cannot be
described in terms of uh cartisian
coordinates but still we'll discover
that we can find a gamma which has the
right
property all right uh so the main
purpose of this was just to show you
that derivatives of tensors are not
themselves tensors you have to do
something
else uh I'll give you the general rule
I'll tell you what the general rule is
in particular for tensors with lower
well I'll give you the general rule
right
now
um for things with lower
components for things with lower
components uh it's this is um
yeah because the coordinates vary from
place to place
there are contributions of this
type for each one of the components and
I'll show you how it works and then
we'll see if we can find out any piece
of information about what this gamma
is at some point I'm going to leave for
you a bunch of algebra to work out but
I'll show you what the rules are and
then you can go home and uh check
yourself that uh that I that I have the
right object Okay so
let's here was the way you write a
covariant derivative of a vector what
would happen if I wanted to make a
covariant derivative of a tensor oh
incidentally what's the covariant
derivative of a
scaler that's
easy it's just the ordinary
derivative ordinary derivative is a
tensor okay but for a tensor we have to
do a more complicated
operation let's take some tensor not
necessarily this tensor over here any
tensor with two indices for
example tmn and supposing we want to
find its covariant
derivative
again with respect to again with respect
to Y uh covariant
derivative uh let's give it let's I'll
tell you what I want to change notation
here a little bit I want to call this P
if I call that P I have to call this
P so let's see I have t
MN and I want to take its covariant
derivative with respect to p with
respect to
YP what does it have in it again it
starts out with the ordinary derivative
derivative of
tmn with respect to YP
it starts out with just the ordinary
derivative that's all that would be
there in cartisian coordinates but now
because the coordinates may be varying
from place to place and remember we have
two components here each
component can each uh each index here is
like a vector index and here's the rule
just make a blind eye to n just let's uh
let's make a Blind Eye by circling it in
red did
you
oh I wanted a p over here on this let's
see on one side I want P thank
you yeah p over
here yeah and also over
here right
okay
so we're doing a similar thing now to
tmn first of all let's turn a blind ey
completely to
n
whoops really
blind and we'll do that by circling it
and ignoring it on both sides of the
equation if if there was no in here this
would just be a vector let's write down
what we would do to co to write the
covariant derivative of T the answer
would
be derivative sorry derivative of TM
with respect to YP I'm going to just
never say n derivative
of TM with respect to YP
plus gamma m
gamma
PM gamma
PMR
times
t
r
n look what I've done I've done exactly
what I did over
here except with an extra index here
just riding along just traveling along
for the ride
doing
nothing but that's not the whole story
the rest of the story is to add another
term in which you take a b you turn a
blind eye to the index
M so now let's be blind to
M ignore
it and write another term which will be
gamma p n now the index interest is n
again
R and
T M
R let's see this time
we which one did we
out uh yeah that was okay that that
stays like that turn the Blind Eye to M
now now we turn the Blind Eye to M so M
just went along for the over here in the
second
term for each index let's concentrate on
covariant indices for each index in a
tensor no matter how many of them are
there are when you covariant
differentiate it you get another term
with a gamma times the tensor
itself and the other terms those the
terms are simply one by one you
go through the various indices turning a
blind eye to all the other indices
that's the
ruley this
one
pm and r n went along for the
ride in other words let's just let's
um let's let's just erase in over here
for first of all let's get rid of this I
don't want to erase it because I don't
want to have to write it again but just
forget it and let's erase
in then this would just be exactly the
way a vector
transformed all right but let's put back
the blind index now n n
okay now let's that's
here
and
let's turn our Blind Eye to the other
index which one is the other one now uh
I lost
track yeah but
uh
[Music]
uh yeah in the second term the Blind Eye
is turned to the m index so let's erase
it on both Sid
sides and notice again this is
transforming exactly the same way that a
vector would transform with an index
n you put them
together and you have the full
transformation property or not the full
transformation the full covariant
derivative of a tensor if there were
more indices you would simply have more
terms exactly the same form gamas time
T's but index by index you would pretend
it was a vector and transform it or or
do the same thing that's the covariant
derivative the derivative of T occurs in
the first term
yeah yeah yeah
yeah that's right
so in particular here's an interesting
fact you could have a tensor with
completely constant components from
point to point then there would be no
derivatives but still the covariant
derivative of the tensor would be not
zero somehow this tensor has a coari
derivative whatever that means I'm going
to show you an example in a moment even
though the components of the tensor are
absolutely constant now let me give you
an example of such a
situation T no not in
general uh did I get them in the wrong
place you are right I did get him in the
wrong place TMR I think
right let's see n is on the right side
here and M should be on the left side
here so that should be like
that
right here uh derivative yes you're
right good thank
you
okay but the basic rule is the same as
the rule for vectors except you go
through it one by one doing to each IND
index what you did to the single Vector
index here a scalar having no indices
requires no extra term all right now
let's let's focus on this fact that
there can be tensors in particular
vectors Let's uh let's focus on vectors
now uh vectors whose components are
completely
constant in curved coordinates and yet
the covariant derivative is not equal to
zero I have a question yeah I assume
that you
can you can swap an index with repeated
index yeah
middle if you want no you can't put an R
here no no here t t NR would been okay
NR it is
NR you want no no no no no no no not
okay not okay not okay um you can't
interchange in general no no that's a
repeated index n is not a repeated index
R well that means you can change it to S
if you like but you can't interchange it
with
n you can give it a different name
that's
fine okay but you can't you can't
substitute one index for another okay
unless it happens to be a symmetric uh
tensor of some sort in which case tab is
the same as
TBA okay okay uh let me give you an
example of a tensor or a vector which is
clearly not constant even though the
derivatives of its components are
zero go to Polar coordinates in polar
coordinates here's our polar
coordinates and let's consider a vector
with the following property yeah uh
ignore the origin the origin as I said
is a nasty point so we'll forget the
origin not important but this Vector
has zero for its Theta component what
would a Theta component mean a Theta
component of a vector the radial
component of a vector means the
component along the radial axis the
Theta component of vector means a
component along the tangential
Direction all right so now I have a
vector where the Theta component let's
call it V Theta is identically equal to
zero all right but the radial component
let's say is equal to
one what does that Vector look
like it has a radial it has no Theta
component anywhere
everywhere is on the
plane its radial component is the same
equal to
one but it points outward from the
origin that's a vector which has radial
component equal to 1 and Theta component
equal to zero quite obviously the
components are
constant the components are constant one
and zero but nobody would look at that
and say that the vector field was
constant it's varying from place to
place obviously the vector over here is
different than it is over here so here's
an example uh of
a vector field whose components are
constant in a particular set of
coordinates their components would not
be constant in cartisian coordinates in
cartisian coordinates here it has an X
component here it doesn't have an X
component but in polar coordinates the
components are completely constant and
yet the vector is not constant
right what would happen if we calculated
the covariant derivative of this Vector
we would find that it's not
zero we would find that it's not zero
and so it's the covariant derivative
which picks up the real geometric fact
that the that the vector varies from
place to place now I haven't told you
what gamma is gamma is an object which
can be constructed from the components
of the
um uh of the metric of the metric tensor
so let's see if we can make a little bit
of progress in finding out what gamma
is okay what about the covariant
derivative of the metric tensor
itself uh let's go to cartisian
coordinat Ates first in cartisian
coordinates the metric tensor is what
what is the metric tensor in cartisian
coordinates it's just Delta
MN it really is constant from place to
place uh in cartisian coordinates it's
absolutely
constant and incidentally if a object is
constant in cartisian coordinates where
the coordinates don't flop around and
change direction
if an object is constant in cartisian
coordinates from place to place then
it's really
constant have a nonat withian
coordinates no no cartisian coordinates
means coordinates in which the metric
tensor is Delta
MN it's not just that you've drawn it's
not just that they've laid out
coordinates like this it means that the
metric tensor is equal to Delta
MN that's what what I mean it means the
space is flat and it means that the
uh
orian I mean when I when I speak about
cartisian coordinates I'm now speaking
about the flat back
Blackboard I'm speaking about a flat
space with
rectangular cartisian coordinates that's
what I mean so the metric tensor if I
took some other space for example I take
the surface of a sphere and I lay it out
on a plane by
um uh um mercada
projection okay then you draw the
mercada projection and it looks like it
has cartisian coordinates but the metric
tensor is not constant from place to
place that's why
um uh Greenland looks bigger than uh
South America because the metric is not
uniform from place to place okay what I
mean by cartisian coordinates I mean
cartisian coordinates in flat space the
metric is just Delta MN right this is
clearly
constant and
if the space is identical at all places
the coordinates don't flop
around the D not only is the derivative
of the metric tensor equal to zero it
makes good sense to say the to expect
that the um that the real physic uh the
the um Co iant derivative of the metric
tensor is also
zero
uh what would it be if not zero if
everything is exactly the same from
point to point and the space is
completely flat so it's natural to
expect that the covariant derivative of
the metric tensor let's write it Dr of
gmn of Y is equal to zero now why do I
write that I
expect that the covariant derivative is
going to be zero in the x
coordinates but the covariant derivative
is supposed to be a tensor and if a
tensor is zero in one set of coordinates
it will be zero in all coordinates so it
better be that if I've defined the
covariant derivative
correctly then in flat space like this
it had better be that the covariant
derivative of gmn is also equal to zero
that's a property of the metric tensor
that its covariant derivative is equal
to
zero which is another way of saying
physically it doesn't vary from place to
place and in particular in cartisian
coordinates and flat space it doesn't
vary at all okay let's assume that's
true let's take that as given that the
covariant derivative of the metric is
equal to zero and let's see what it says
and we'll do it by well just by
substitution here
uh
gmn
gns and GM R I
think and this should be equal to
zero if the covariant derivative of the
metric is equal to
zero this is an identity which if you
struggle with it a little bit you can
actually solve it for gamas in terms of
derivatives of
G
uh I'm not going to work it out on the
Blackboard it's a little bit tedious you
can either look it up in a book or you
can try working it out yourself uh a few
tricks you need to write down you need
to write down a few uh I'll I'll tell
you what to do when we get
I'll tell you what the solution of this
equation is this regard this as a Sol as
an equation for the gamas it's an
equation for gamas in terms of G's and
in terms of derivatives of G's that's
what it
is uh since G with lower indices
multiplies gamma here supposing I wanted
to get rid of G with lower index I have
something which uh let's first of all
write that this thing here is equal to
minus derivative of G what was it oh
yeah yeah I lost the uh uh derivative
with respect to
YP of G MN yes yeah approximately that
okay so here I have an equation if it
didn't have two terms like this it would
be very easy to solve I would just
multiply by the inverse of G I have a
gamma times a G and G is an invertible
Matrix so all I would have to do is run
through the invertible Matrix and I
would wind up with a G inverse I would
wind up with a gamma something like
PMS with a derivative of G on this side
and a g inverse lower components here
here and a g with upper components
here just by inverting G and bringing it
over to the other side it would bring an
inverse of G to the other side is that
clear what we're doing but because there
are two terms here it's more complicated
it's more complicated I'm going to write
down the answer and then what you do is
you go home and you check that the
answer that I write down satisfies this
relationship so I'm going to write down
what gamma is and it's your job to go
home and check that if you plug in for
gamma it really does satisfy this
condition so I'm going to write down
what it is anybody know what these
things are called the gamas I forgot to
tell
you they're called christopal
symbols they're called
connections aine
connection christofel symbols whatever
you
like christopal symbols not christofel
not gam they're called gamas
too yeah Lot G what's that there a lot
of things called G yeah but not too many
of them with three indices like that so
right so if you want to give them the
right name their right name is
christophel symbol there are all kinds
of things which are called connections
they're all similar and they're all
related are they're all they all are
doing the same kind of job in various
contexts but in GE omry in this metric
geometry like this these objects are
called christopal
symbols
symb yeah but they're just related by
raising and lowering indices yeah I just
notic looks like you can lower
indices which two
terms yeah yeah you could indeed you
could pull this this could be written
this could be written as G
p
m with another index in
downstairs right and how about this one
over here this one could be written as
gamma
p uh
n
m they're identical except one of them
has MN the other one has n m
okay so they're not the same in general
they're not the same you can't you can't
obviously equate them they're not the
same and for that reason you can't just
solve this equation by
saying that this thing is basically half
of this thing not so it's more
complicated but I'll write down what the
answer is and uh you can check
that in
fact uh yeah let's write down the
answer all
right I'm going to use other letters now
so that we don't confuse confus them
with the letters here I'll use a b and
c gamma a b c is equal
to
12 g a D I need another letter of the
alphabet that's going to be a summation
index and then it's the sum of three
terms three terms each one has a
derivative each term has a g with a
super index here upstairs index and then
derivatives of G with lower indices it's
just the indices are a little bit
intricate uh g a d time uh the partial
of the Der derivative of G let's see
what is it uh
d
c with respect to
XB d c with respect to
XB plus the partial of
G now let's see wherever I see B see G
DB with respect to x
c minus the derivative of
GBC with respect to
XD
yeah y coordinat oh sorry depending on
whether in any coordinate system it has
this form right so if I was working in
the Y coordinates I would put y there
right but then of course I would use the
metric in y-coordinates
metric and Y coordinates if I wanted
these and this would be the christopal
symbol and y-coordinates now the
christopal symbol itself is not a
tensor it's not a
tensor uh for example one way to see
that it's not a tensor is if we were in
conventional cartisian coordinates in
flat space the derivatives in in with X
with x
coordinates the derivatives of G are all
zero so this whole thing would be zero
in x coordinates on the other hand if we
changed coordinates to some other kind
of curvy linear coordinates the G's
would not be constant anymore and the
christopal symbol would not be zero so
the christopal symbol is not a T but
it's to be used in conjunction with
tensors to construct covariant
derivatives that's it that's its whole
goal in life is to be used together with
the rules that I outlined for
constructing derivatives of tensors it's
the extra term or it's a piece of the
extra term which is there because the
coordinates Wiggle from places to place
from place to
place all right so your job then is to
take this expression feed it into to
here and check that what you get on the
left hand side is just DG by
Dy that's the
uh I don't remember two and
Aus forgot I don't
remember it's a I don't I don't know I'm
not sure why if we plug it in it ought
to
work I don't
remember oh yeah and important thing is
look at the structure of
it um the two the BC components in one
term you have B
downstairs in the other term you have C
downstairs those come in with plus sign
and then the last component has D
downstairs okay you can you can play
with it and uh and work it out but the
important thing about it it's not so
important exactly what it is you can
memorize it if you like or don't
memorize it but the important thing is
it is the connection it is the object
which allows you to differentiate
tensors derivative of
v m with respect to X and
plus gamma
n
uh
Mr
VR covariant
derivative
okay fun strange question
down indic
are and then you have indices above over
here on the
right is aair index okay it's a
downstairs IND it's upstairs in y but
because it's below the line it's
downstairs right you have three
downstairs
indices but it isn't obvious to me what
the order of those indices should be
written as you wrot as
downstairs you mean this one too
no just just a part inside brackets
basically we have three downstairs
indices which should I call that BBC or
BCB if I was thinking of it as one one
with it's not symmetric with respect to
them it is symmetric with respect to B
and
C it's symmetric with respect to to B
and C but not with respect to D and that
you can see because there's a minus sign
here among other
thingses yeah okay it does until we
contract it with the G yeah so we could
call it gamma b
c
d okay so you would
put
BCD no it's got two it's got two
downstairs indices plus a third one okay
you just have to remember which one goes
where and it happens if you look at it
carefully you'll see that it's
interchange symmetric with respect to B
and C but not with respect to
D I
thought yeah yeah but nevertheless we
have to give this thing name in here
that gets multiplied by g a
d and then the D disappears but before
we disappear it we give it a
name Okay
g it happens in this case it does yeah
it happens in this case and
furthermore furthermore you can use
gamma to um to differentiate
contravariant tensors
also for example I'll show you the rule
the same
object as it happens enters into the
derivative of contravariant
tensors contravariant components of
tensors for example if you have a vector
with an index n now it has an upper
index in then again y
components and you want to differentiate
it with respect to y
m that itself is not a tensor for the
same reasons the contravariant
components also depend on the direction
of the axes so as the axes move around
you've got to keep track of that and the
derivative of the contravariant
components is not are not themselves
tensors right this would be a tensor
with one upper index and one lower index
but it's not you have to add something
to it and the thing you have to add to
it has gamma now it has a lower index
M an upper index
n we're going to have to put in another
index let's call it R that's going to be
a summation index and then a
VR of
Y so the same set of objects
is useful in differentiating
um uh things with upper
indices once you construct this family
of objects and there's a lot of them how
many of them are there in
three-dimensional Space 3 * 3 * 3 27 of
them in four dimensional space it's 64
of course they're not all
independent they do have some symmetries
but there's a lot of components and so
if you're actually doing some
computation you might want to write them
all down in your notebook uh make a list
of them what they are what their values
are and then St playing with them so
it's it's a a tedious business working
out these things but the logic it's the
logic that I want you to understand that
differentiating tensors and doing it in
a way that gives you back tensors is a
slightly complicated process that
involves a new thing namely the
so-called connection or christopal
symbol that's the basic question okay
yeah so the reason the reason that the
metric has a zero coari derivative is
because it's zero in cesan and it also
must be zero yeah it makes a lot of
sense to say that in the cartisian
coordinates in flat
space flat space is the same everywhere
it makes a lot of sense to say the basic
object in that space is constant from
position to position you don't have to
Define it that way you could have
defined some crazy definition but in
flat homogeneous space the Blackboard
going on and on
forever uh perfectly flat and perfectly
homogeneous homogeneous means the same
everywhere uh it makes good sense to say
that the metric has no variation from
place to
place so in the flat SP
coordinates the tensor that you would
make by differentiating the metric would
be
zero once it's zero in one coordinate
system if it's a tensor then it has to
be zero in all coordinate systems and so
one comes to the conclusion that uh that
the covariant derivative of the metric
should be zero that's what we use to um
to find
a basic relationship which when solved
gives us this
formula yeah do you have a
a way of looking at the at the
derivative the covariant derivative of a
vector that that doesn't involve the
coordinates in other words you're you're
taking the nearby things and doing
something to them and what precisely is
it I mean here we've gotten a lot of
information well okay yeah it's very
hard to describe what you're doing
without introducing coordinates but
maybe it helps a little bit the
following
idea any
space
any ranian space like this spaces with
metrics like this called ranian spaces
any ranian
space curved or not
curved locally that means if you look at
a very small patch of it looks like flat
space is indistinguishable from Flat
space for small enough region that means
on a small region there you you can
introduce cartisian
coordinates you can introduce
perpendicular
coordinates and you can even do it so
that the derivative of so that first of
all so that the metric at that point is
Delta
MN by introducing you know on the
surface of the Earth the Earth is not
flat but uh just drawing you know two
perpendicular great circles
basically wouldn't even realize they
were great circles if we're uh looking
in some small region we just think the
straight lines and introduce locally in
the vicinity of a point cartisian
coordinates then the metric at that
point at that point the metric will just
be Delta
MN but it's possible to do even a little
better than just saying that the metric
is Delta MN at a point it's also
possible to keep the coordinates
straight enough and perpendicular enough
so that the derivatives of the metric at
that point at a single point or zero so
that up to First derivatives the metric
is constant and
uh and just of the form Delta
MN at a particular point of
space with a given set of well with a
given space you can't make the metric
constant everywhere unless the space
happens to be flat if the space is flat
you can make the metric like this
everywhere but if it's not flat you can
go to a particular point and do that now
there was a reason why I raised that I
forgot what the question was though
talking about
the
thear
yeah covariant derivative of
what Vector a
vector Okay so what it means at such a
point if you go to these locally
cartisian coordinates then the locally
cartisian coordinates like this the
derivatives of g at that point are all
equal to zero and at that point focusing
on that particular point the covariant
derivative is just the ordinary
derivative in those coordinates in other
words you erect as close as you can get
the flat space the flat coord
coordinates through cartisian
coordinates you can you can't do that
everywhere
simultaneously but you can do it in a
tiny little region and then the
covariant derivative is just the
ordinary derivative in those kind of
coordinates so it's telling you how the
vector it's telling you how the vector
varies in coordinates which are as
flattened out as is possible to make how
the vector is turning and growing at the
same time y turning in each direction
right
that's right yeah so if gamma is zero is
that a definition for flat
space uh no no no that's not quite
right if you take flat space and you use
curvy linear coordinates then gamma is
not equal to zero remember gamma is not
a
tensor uh it depends both on the nature
of the space and the coordinates that
you
use in flat space what is true
is that it's possible to find
coordinates in which gamma is equal to
zero but it's also possible to make
coordinates in which it's not equal to
zero uh here's an exercise work out the
gamas for Polar
coordinates there are gamas for Polar
coordinates why is that it's because at
least one of the components of the
metric gr
RR is equal to R 2 that means the Der
ative of grr with respect to R is not
equal to
zero that begins to give you the
possibility of having a christopal
symbol in polar coordinates and there is
a christopal symbol in polar coordinates
that just means in polar coordinates
when you differentiate a vector you have
to include uh remember remember what
happened with the vector which had
constant components in polar coordinates
it wasn't really constant
so in polar coordinates in flat space
covariant derivatives are not entirely
trivial and that means that there are
christopal symbols for Polar coordinates
what is true for flat space is that you
can find coordinates namely just your
Good Old rectangular cartisian
coordinates in which the metric is just
Delta MN in which all the christopal
symbols are zero in a general curved
space you cannot do that in a general
curved space in general the christopal
symbols will not be zero
yeah say it
again external you mean exterior
derivative completely different
thing it is a kind of derivative for
sure but
uh um
the exterior derivative is a
tensor you know what the exterior
derivative of a vector
is in three
dimensions it's the curl of the
vector it's called an exterior
derivative so we won't get into that
now yeah the exterior derivative is a
tensor but um
um if we ever need it we'll come through
it let's
uh I don't want to stop tonight I want
to continue tonight because I want to
get finished with
this with the mathematics so that we can
start thinking about physics all right
let's
um take let's see what do we need to do
here
yeah supposing I have some
curve now let's start with ordinary flat
space ordinary conventional flat space I
have some Vector fields which varies
from place to place in particular I can
evaluate that field along the curve and
I want to know how the vector field
varies just along the
curve ordinary flat space what do I do I
want to know how the components of the
vector vary along the
curve this is easy we just write the
field V let's say the nth component of
it again in as a function of Y
Y and I want to know how it varies first
of all I want to invent a parameter that
varies along the curve what's a good
parameter that varies along a curve Arc
Length length along the curve we can
start here and call it zero and then
measure uh in some units whatever units
we like distance along the curve and of
course we call that
s in the same sense that we call DS
squared the square of a little interval
we can invent a variable along the curve
which is just Arc Length along the
curve I would like along the curve to
ask how V is varying how do I do that
well I differentiate it well let's take
first a scalar take a scalar how does a
scalar vary along the curve it's
derivative along the curve in particular
it's derivative with respect to the
parameter s
we evaluate it on the curve and I want
to differentiate it with respect to S so
I'd like to find along the curve the
derivative of f with respect to S
whoops just telling me how five varies
well if I know how how five varies
throughout the geometry I just write d
by DS the DX
DX M let's say
that's the partial derivative and then
what do I do to make it into the
derivative along the
curve we multiply it by
DXM by
DS so everywhere's along the
curve there's an object DXM by
DS that of course is a vector DXM is a
little vector and when I divide it by DS
It's s is a scalar just the distance
along the curve DXM by DS is a vector
you know what that Vector is
called uh the slope would be Dy by DX I
mean dx1 by dx2 so it's connected with
the slope but it's not quite the slope
it's a vector first of it's not a number
it's a vector it has two
components uh dx1 by DS and dx2 by DS
okay let's look at it a little more
closely here we are along the curve we
take a little interval of size DS and we
look at DX here's DX it's the vector DX
along here first of all what direction
is it
in Tangent to the vector tangent to the
curve and how long is it
what's the length of DX by
DS yeah one one why is
that well it's one it's a unit Vector
along the curve it's called the tangent
Vector it is the tangent Vector along
the curve a unit Vector along the curve
called a tangent Vector okay all right
so that's right here's what you do if
you want to differentiate
F along X sorry along s you
differentiate it with respect to the
coordinates that gives you a covariant
vector and you multiply it by the Contra
contravariant Vector DX by D DS and that
gives you the derivative of f with
respect to
S right very
simple now supposing we want to
differentiate a vector or a vector not a
tensor not a um a scaler but a tensor in
particular a
vector along a
curve well you might think this right
thing to do is basically the same thing
take the vector v let's take a uh let's
take a um a uh contrarian
Vector it depends on X I guess well X
and Y are the same thing here uh
X right and now what do I do with it
well differentiate it with respect to
position x uh what do we call it uh x
what n
m time
DXM by
DS this actually gives us the derivative
of the component of V
with respect to S but you would you
guess that this is a
tensor it's not likely to be a tensor
because the whole thing is not likely to
be a tensor because the VN by DXM is not
a
tensor remember the ordinary derivative
of components of tensors is not itself a
tensor so this object is not a tensor it
doesn't
represent let let's uh let's see why
well it's the usual
reason even if V were completely
constant along the
curve what would that mean that would
mean it's completely constant pointing
in the same direction everywhere as
along the curve because the coordinates
flop not because the curve is floppy
incidentally but because the coordinates
are
floppy DV by DX won't be zero and so
even for a vector which was absolutely
constant
in space like this this wouldn't be zero
you're not assuming that's that's those
are cartisian coord no I'm not assuming
they're cartisian coordinates right no
particularly
not no I I guess I should have stuck
with my
convention uh X being cartisian so then
we should use y
here all right so let's use y
well what can I do to make a vector out
of this a tensor out of it a tensor uh
that varies along the curve well we just
replace this by the covariant derivative
wherever you see ordinary derivative
replace it by covariant derivative at
least the covariant derivative has the
property that if the vector isn't really
varying the covariant derivative is zero
all right so if we replace this by the
covariant derivative that's
just covariant derivative with respect
to
M
uh of
v n of Y times the tangent
Vector that we can think of as the
covariant derivative the notation for it
is it's the covariant derivative with
respect to the parameter s of v
n we've defined a covariant derivative
of a vector along a
curve how you just take the ordinary
covariant derivative and you multiply it
by the tangent Vector tangent Vector
just tells you what different what
direction you're differentiating in
you take a covariant derivative and that
defines the covariant the path
derivative along the curve important
concept okay in particular it has the
property that in cartisian space in flat
space with cartisian coordinates if the
components are constant then the curve
then the vector doesn't vary along the
curve okay um
that's the notion of
the covariant derivative of a vector
along a curve
just
good
um let's write out let's write it out in
detail let's write it out in
detail what is it it's the derivative of
VN with respect to
ym times
well let's add the other term what's the
other term all right tell me where to
put the gam the indices of the
gamas where does the N index
go it's upstairs better go upstairs in
the gamma the M index has to go
downstairs and then we need another
index and write
VR that's the covariant derivative of
V then we have to multiply it by the
tangent vector VOR so let's multiply it
here by the tangent Vector plus
Dy M by
DS d
ym by
DS what is this thing over here the
derivative of the component the nth
component with respect to Y time Dy by
DS chain rule right right this object
over here is just the derivative the
ordinary derivative the ordinary
derivative with respect to
S of
VN so along the curve we differentiates
the first term but then there's another
term and the other term
is gamma
NMR the vector that we're
differentiating times the tangent vector
so if I have a vector which is defined
along a curve and I want to
differentiate it along the curve in a
way that makes it a tensor I just
differentiate its components and then I
hit it with a gamma along the curve the
gamma is defined along the curve time VR
and also multiply by the tangent vector
see the
pattern okay now let's go another
step let's ask how the tangent Vector
varies along the curve for V Let's just
put in the tangent Vector itself and
then I would be asking how the tangent
Vector varies along a
curve here's the tangent vector
and obviously in general the tangent
Vector varies from place to place in
particular if the curve is a curve the
uh in the flat Blackboard the curve is
really a curve then the tangent Vector
varies we can work out the covariant
derivative of the tangent Vector let's
do it what's the component of the
tangent
Vector for
VN we're going to
substitute D YN n by DS that's the
component of the tangent vector and I'm
now Computing the covariant derivative
of the tangent Vector
itself the covariant derivative along
the curve so let's just plug it
in first of all what do I get for dvn by
DS that becomes the second derivative of
YN with respect to
s it's just the derivative with respect
to S of the derivative of y with respect
to S so that's a second
derivative a certain second derivative
of y along the path length and then
what's the other
term
gamma Mr
RN let's write down what is it d
ym by
DS and then V is just Dy
R by
DS so the first
term is just the second derivative of y
with respect to
S and the second term look at it that
has an m and an R downstairs it has a Dy
by DS a tangent Vector the MTH component
and a tangent Vector the rth component
nice and symmetric with respect to these
two and it has an extra index
representing
the uncontracted index here this is the
covariant derivative of a tangent
Vector what would and the covariant
derivative of tangent Vector is a tensor
that means if it's zero in any reference
frame it's zero in every reference frame
what do you expect the covariant
derivative of the tangent Vector of a
straight line to
be zero if I have a straight line in
flat space
the tangent Vector is the same
everywhere
is so if I am in flat space and I have
some funny
coordinates I have some funny
coordinates which aren't ordinary flat
uh you know ordinary cartisian
coordinates but I give you the tangent
Vector I give you the components of the
tangent vector and the christopal
symbols and so forth that's what you
know how do you test if it's a straight
line its components are not constant
because the coordinates aren't constant
they flop around how do I test whether
uh whether my
Vector uh sorry whether my tangent
whether my tangent Vector whether the
whether the curve is a straight line
well I compute the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector and if it's zero
all along the line All Along The Curve
then that curve is a straight line it's
just telling me that the Tang Vector is
unchanging as I go along the line you
could do this with funny coordinates
even if those coordinates AR in flat
flat coordinates now can it be that in
curved space really curved space a
general space which cannot be brought to
the flat
form because there's some obstruction
called curvature which it doesn't look
like we'll get to tonight but can it be
that the covariant derivative of a
tangent vector can be zero anyway even
though the space is not flat what would
you
guess
yes what are curves whose tangent
vectors are coari constant covariant
constant is another way of saying the
covariant derivative of the tangent
Vector is zero here it is where is it
here it
is supposing I have a
curve a curve means some y a curve means
a curve Y is and along the curve the
curve has a set of coordinates y that
depend on how far along the curve you
are everywhere's along the curve Y is
given
here's here's the tangent
Vector can it be that the covariant
derivative of the tangent Vector is zero
it certainly won't be true for every
curve in flat spec space it's only true
for straight
lines can it be true in a general curve
space that you can find curves special
curves which have the property that the
covariant derivative along them is zero
covariant derivative of the tangent
Vector the answer is yes
and those curves have a
name
geodesics geodesics are if you like the
straightest possible Curves in the space
they have the property that the
covariant derivative of the tangent
Vector is zero in particular that means
if you take coordinates locally which
are as flat as possible then along then
the components of the vector are
constant for a little ways until the
curve until the comp until the
coordinates start to
bend but a geodesic that's the general
definition of a geodesic a geodesic is
one is a curve whose tangent Vector is
covariant constant coari constant means
that
it's that the covariant derivative of
the tangent Vector is equal to
zero
uh and that's it that's the uh that's
the definition of a
geodesic in a certain sense it's the
straightest possible curve in the space
or it's a family of Curves yeah quick
question you define this all in terms of
a CO iant derivative yes could you just
as
arbitrarily used a contravariant
derivative and get to the same point yes
you could have used uh yeah we could
have used sure sure definitely we could
have used we could have used the
contravariant defin coar wait sorry just
a moment the term covariant derivative
does not mean that the object is a
covariant vector completely different
use of the word it's
unfortunate this is the covariant
derivative of a contravariant
component too bad that's the way it
is but like the key point is this the
inclusion of this gamut thing yeah
that's right that's right
now just to just to tell you where this
is going let me tell you where this is
going um
straight lines in
SpaceTime in special relativity special
relativity SpaceTime is
flat straight lines in SpaceTime are the
orbits of particles that have no forces
on
them okay the orbits of particles that
have gravitational forces on them
are geodesics in SpaceTime that that
means they satisfy equations like this
now if you look at this equation and you
think of path length along a world
line as being like time taking off time
along the world line and this is almost
like acceleration it is it basically is
acceleration
the we don't want to prove this now we
just want to tell you where it's going
this looks like the second derivative of
a coordinate with respect to a parameter
and that parameter could be proper time
it would be proper time so it's
essentially a relativistic version of
acceleration what does it say it says
that acceleration is equal to something
on the right hand side what would you
call that thing on the right hand
side
Force right so where we're going
eventually is that this is the equation
which the determines the orbits of
particles in a gravitational
field the force is
proportional first of all to the
christopal symbol that's the most
important thing about
it uh forget these things for a
moment they're there they're important
but uh here's the important thing what
does this contain it contains
derivatives of the metric with respect
to
position how about Newton's equations
what's Newton's equations for the motion
of a particle in a gravitational
field it's FAL ma right all right uh F
equal f ma is mass time the second
derivative of position let's call
position y with respect to
time it looks sort of like this and then
what's on the right hand
side the gravitational force but what is
a gravitational force proportional
to well in general in a general
gravitational field it's proportional to
the mass times the derivative
of the potential the gravitational
potential let's call it let's give it a
name fi or V I don't know v u v with
respect to
Y masses cancel
out you can see there's some similarity
an acceleration type term being related
to derivatives of something with respect
to position what are the christopal
symbols they're composed out of
derivatives of the metric with respect
to position so somehow we're going to
find that the derivatives of the metric
with respect to
position are the analogues of the
Newtonian gravitational force that's
where we're going so I thought I would
tell you rather than just blindly write
formulas on the
Blackboard particles move on geodesics
which means the straightest possible
paths in space
time but of course you can't have a
completely straight path in a curved
space and the deviation from what you
might think of as
straight is proportional to these gamas
so the gamas are very very closely
related to gravitational force they are
the gravit
force uh what else can we say at this
point yeah we haven't gotten around to
curvature yet but we have all the
apparatus that we need we need one more
concept uh namely the concept of
parallel transport but I will tell you
what that is next
time uh parallel transport and then we
will get to the idea of curvature we
have some ideas that are going to be
useful for how particles move next we
need to understand more deeply the
obstruction to spaces being flat to
flattening them out and that's
curvature okay we're
[Music]
done the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu